Soviet Union True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church Subject Files, 1955-2006
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church Subject Files
1955-2006
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
34
The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
2 A4 document boxes
The Soviet Union True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church Subject Files contain a variety of materials on the history, life, and persecution of True Orthodox clergy and believers in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
From the beginning of the post-World War II period until approximately 2006, Keston obtained materials pertaining to persecution of the True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
The Russian True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church emerged in the 1920s as opposition to the official Russian Orthodox Church and included Orthodox hierarchs and clergy who refused to cooperate with Soviet authorities. For rejecting Metropolitan Sergius’ 1927 declaration on the official Russian Orthodox Church’s loyalty to the Soviet regime, the group faced severe persecution and members were forced underground. By the end of 1930s, the True Orthodox Church lost most of her hierarchs and clergy to execution and resorted to secret ordinations in camps and catacombs. Between 1943 and 1946, authorities discovered and eradicated many True Orthodox communities which clandestinely existed in remote locations in parts of the Soviet Union.
Despite severe persecution, the Catacomb Church secretly held local Councils in 1928, 1948, and 1961. After World War II, the True Orthodox community “andreevtsy” founded by Archbishop Andrei Ufimskii became the most active. Between 1971 and 1981, small True Orthodox councils secretly assembled every two to three years, usually with only three or four bishops in attendance.
Their underground status made it impossible for the True Orthodox Church to exist as an organization. From 1948 to 1974, the Catacomb Church regarded the Primate of the Russian Orthodox Church Outside of Russia (ROCOR) as head of the True Orthodox Church in the Soviet Union. ROCOR broke from the official Russian Orthodox Church after her hierarchy rejected the 1927 declaration on cooperation with the Soviet state. In 1934, Metropolitan Sergius forbade the hierarchs and clergy of ROCOR to serve, making the schism official.
The Orthodox Church Outside of Russia recognizes the True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church in the Soviet Union as a part of the one and free Russian Orthodox Church. Despite the lack of contacts between the Churches during the Cold War, a significant number of Catacomb communities in the Soviet Union identified themselves as a part of ROCOR. During Perestroika, the interest in ROCOR increased among both Soviet dissidents and Orthodox clergy critical of the policies of the Moscow Patriarchate. In the 1980s, ROCOR hierarchs ordained bishops for True Orthodox communities in the Soviet Union. Official ROCOR parishes appeared in the Soviet Union after 1990. However, they faced strong resistance from the official Church, which did not want to compete or lose property. State authorities sided with the Moscow Patriarchate on the issue of property.
The 1997 Russian Law on Freedom of Religion and Religious Organizations caused a disagreement between ROCOR hierarchs. In 2002-2003, the Church divided into the Russian Orthodox Church Outside of Russia headed by Metropolitan Laurus, wishing to reconcile with the Moscow Patriarchate; the Russian Orthodox Autonomous Church headed by Metropolitan Valentin; and the Russian Orthodox Church in Exile headed by Metropolitan Vitalii. In 2007, ROCOR headed by Metropolitan Laurus and the Moscow Patriarchate restored their canonical communion.
True Orthodox churches in modern Russia do not belong to a common organization or have a common administration. They include more than 20 catacomb hierarchies and unregistered parishes as well as independent priests, monks, and communities. Because of years of persecution, many True Orthodox communities lack head bishop or parish clergy. In the early 1990s, Catacomb Church communities in Omsk, Voronezh, Kuban, and other parts of the former Soviet Union legalized their status with registration. However, many True Orthodox communities that never trusted the authorities remained unregistered.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church Subject Files contain materials on the history, life, and persecution of True Orthodox clergy and believers in the Soviet Union and Post-Soviet Russia. The materials cover a period from 1955 to 2006, with the bulk from 1977 to 1992.
The topics include but are not limited to the situation of True Orthodox (Catacomb) churches in Abkhazia, the Republic of Komi, and other regions; life of True Orthodox Christian women in Mordovian labor camps; reports on disputes over the transfer of property to the Russian Orthodox Church of the Moscow Patriarchate; and appeals to the members of parliamentary commission for freedom of conscience, Fr. Gleb Yakunin and Fr. Vyacheslav Polosin.
The files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, reports, official correspondence, and publications.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church Subject Files in folders, some of which were organized by categories. This original filing system has been preserved. Unsorted materials have been organized by topic and filed chronologically. The materials are in good conditions.
The Soviet Union True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church Subject Files are arranged into two series: I. General and II. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 34.
Related Resources
Related references
Bourdeaux, Michael., and S. B. Filatov. Sovremennai︠a︡ religioznai︠a︡ zhizn)' Rossii: opyt sistematicheskogo opisanii︠a︡. Moskva: Logos, 2003.
Moss, Vladimir (Anthony Edward St. George). The Imperishable Word: True Orthodox Christianity in the Twentieth Century. U.K: Gresham Books, 1980.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Amvrosiiămp;&, arkhiepiskop Gotfskiiămp;& IPKh, 1967-; IAkunin, Gleb, 1935-2014.; Lapkin, I. T (Ignatiĭ Tikhonovich); Mikhail, Archbishop, 1911-1974.; Osipova, I. I. (Irina Ivanovna); Polosin, A. V. (Ali Vi︠a︡cheslav), 1956-
Subjects (Organizations)
Istinno-pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)'.; Orthodox Eastern Church.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov -- History -- 20th century.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov zagranitse -- History.
Places
Soviet Union -- Church history.
Subjects
Church and state -- Soviet Union.; Communism and religion -- Soviet Union.; Persecution -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Publications.; References.
- General, 1963-2006, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains unofficially circulated information, including records, reports, and manuscripts on various aspects of the life of True Orthodox Christians in the Soviet Union.
  The series is in good condition.
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. General, 1963-1987, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. History, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Canon Law. Basic Regulations, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Sobor (1 of 2), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Sobor (2 of 2), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Relations with the State, 1978, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Local Churches, 1971-1978, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Registration of Churches, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Oppressive Practices against True Orthodox Christians. General, 1977-1978, 1991, 1995, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Oppressive Practices against True Orthodox Christians. Trials., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Oppressive Practices against True Orthodox Christians. Imprisonment., 1970-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Oppressive Practices against True Orthodox Christians. Legal Disabilities, 1991, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Oppressive Practices against True Orthodox Christians. Abuse of Psychiatry, 1977, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Oppressive Practices against True Orthodox Christians. Attacks in Media, 1966, 1968-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church Life. General, 1963, 1968, 1976-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Clergy and Priesthood. General, 1974-1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Individual Clergy. General, 1974-1980, 1992, 1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Individual Clergy. Bishop Amvrosii, 1994-1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Individual Clergy. Chernov, Fr. Antonii, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Individual Clergy. Ershov, Fr. Mikhail, 1974-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. International Contacts. General, 1980, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Support of the Russian Orthodox Church Abroad, 1977, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Relations with Other Denominations, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Women, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Late Soviet and Post-Soviet Period. General, 1990-1992, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Manuscripts. Moss, Vladimir, 1983, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Anonymous Manuscript "Sovetskaia tserkov'", undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Anonymous Manuscript "Tserkov' katakombnaia na zemle rossiiskoi", undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Manuscript. General (1 of 2), ca. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Manuscript. General (2 of 2), 1980, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Published Works. Osipova, Irina "Through Fire of Martyrdom and Flood of Tears", 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Published Articles, 1971, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Samizdat, 1955-1986, undated; 2
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Oppressive Practices against True Orthodox Christians. General, 1974, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Oppressive Practices against True Orthodox Christians. Imprisonment, 1955, 1972-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Samizdat Publications. Vasilevskaia, Vera, "Katakomby XX veka - vospominaniia", undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Samizdat Publications. True Orthodox Christian Newspaper "Za pravoslavie i samoderzhavie", 1986 June 24 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Samizdat Publications. "Pravila po okhrane i zashchite tserkvi gonimoi, katakombnoi", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church. Samizdat Publications. "Ignatii Tikhonovich Lapkin /khronika/", 1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)